Hello.
大家好。
In this session, I'd talk about the kernel hacking for signal tracing.
在這部影片中，我的題目是信號追蹤(signal tracing)。
My name is Leesoo Ahn. and I am currently working as an engineer at a wireless router company.
我的名字是Leesoo Ahn，現於一間無線路由器公司擔任工程師。
I worked as a contributor at GNONE for 2 years from 2018, and I am currently conducting research related to the kernel.
我自2018年起便擔任GNONE的貢獻者，目前正在做與內核(kernal)相關的研究。
I'm sure some of you here already know about Signals.
我相信你們之中有些人已經對信號有所了解。
Signals are one of many inter-process communications that currently exist in Linux
信號是在Linux系統之中，眾多形程間通訊(inter-process communication)之一。
To give a simple example, here are two processes: a parent and a child.
舉例來說，這裡有兩個行程：父行程與子行程。
The parent is sending a message to the child, and this overall picture is IPC.
父行程正在傳送一個訊息給子行程，整體的情況是IPC.
And the message be used in here is Signal.
訊息便是信號的一種。
Of course, children can also respond to their parents.
當然，子行程也可以對父行程做出回應。
It only depends on how the child program is implemented.
取決於子行程是如何被實現(implemented)的。
The situation in the previous example is often what we see in textbooks.
這樣的情況常見於教科書中。
It seems to have no problems and it looks fine, but...
乍看之下並無問題，但是...
There are more complicated situations than these happy situations in actual production.
在現實世界中有比這些範例更加複雜的狀況。
For example, there are cases where completely unrelated processes send a signal to their children,
比方說，有可能數個完全無相關的行程向各自的子行程傳送信號。
and there may be situations where the parent does not receive the signal.
也有可能父行程沒有收到應得的信號。
When we face a issue related in signals, it can be easily solved if you know how to analyze it,
當我們碰到信號相關的問題，如果不知道如何分析信號，將會非常難以解決。
but how can we do it?
我們可以怎麼做？
Several tools are available to analyze these problems.
有一些工具適合用於此類分析此類問題。
The first is a tool you know. GDB is a line-by-lline debugger, and
第一個工具是GDB，GDB是一個逐行除錯器(debugger)。
you can attach it to a process, and you can check the currently running statement line-by-line.
你可以將它連接於一個行程，然後你可以逐行檢查實時的運行資訊。
Also, we can use Strace. Strace is lighter than GDB,
第二，我們也可以使用Strace，它比GDB更加的輕量化。
and it is designed to focus in only System-calls and signals in our tracings.
而且它被設計成專心於追蹤系統呼叫(System-calls)與信號。
Third, we have Ftrace. Unlike GDB and Strace, Ftrace can trace system-wide and can analyze most events occurring in the kernel.
第三，我們有Ftrace，有別於GDB及Strace，Ftrace可以追蹤整個系統(system-wide)及分析幾乎所有內核中的事件。
There must be many other techniques that I am not aware of.
一定有其它的，我所不知的技巧。
But if
但是假如...
the situation I showed you earlier happens
前述的情況發生了。
when the system is booting up, there are more things to consider.
當系統正在啟動(booting up)之時，有更多事情需要考慮。
Tools such as GDB, Strace, and Ftrace are stored in the file system, but if the file system is being mounted at the time the problem occurs, we can't use them, plus,
像是GDB、Strace及Ftrace的工具是存放於檔案系統， 但是假如在檔案系統掛載時出現了錯誤，我們便不能使用這些工具。
The order of execution between the target process and the debuggers should also be considered.
加上，也需要考慮目標行程及除錯器的執行順序。
For example, if we run the debuggers first before the target is executed, analysis wouldn't be made, right?
舉例說，如果我們在目標行程執行前便執行除錯器，分析便是無效的。
Furthermore, in embedded systems, shell access is blocked for security, and we couldn't launch a debugger through a terminal, in such environments.
更進一步，在嵌入式系統中，Shell基於安全因素將會被關閉，因此在這樣的環境中我們將無法透過電腦終端(terminal)執行除錯器。
Besides that, there are a few other things to consider.
除了上述之外，還需要考慮更多事情。
We know it isn't the core of the problem, but It forces us focus to such tiresome tasks, so it's so stressful and annoying.
我們知道這不是問題的核心，單是它迫使我們專注於如此煩人的作業，因此它是極度惱人且有壓力的。
Rather than that, it would be better to focus on the original problem and finish it quickly, right?
比起那樣，專注於原本的問題而且迅速的將它完成才是比較理想的，對吧？
If it is correct to modify the code to solve this problem, wouldn't it be more efficient to access and analyze the signal handling routines in the kernel?
既然修改程式碼去解決問題是正確的作法，那存取及分析內核中的信號處理路線將會是很有效率的做法，對吧？
I approached to it with this thinking.
我將以這樣的思考處理這個問題。
Again, there are two processes here, and the parent is sending a signal to the child. It is a view of signal processing in user level.
復述一次，現在這裡有兩個行程，父行程正在傳送一個訊息給子行程。這是訊號處理(signal processing)的示意圖。
and it is the kernel level view in practice.
而這是現實中內核的顯示內容。
The parent requests a signal from the kernel through the 'kill' system-call, and the kernel handles taken signal, and delivers it to the child.
父行程以"kill"系統呼叫，向內核請求一個信號。內核處理這個信號，並將它傳送給子行程。
If this kernel level is further subdivided, it can be divided into three stages as follows.
將內核等級再次分割，可以分成三個階段。
Of the three stages, we will edit the code in stage-3.
在這三個階段中，我們將編輯第三階段的程式碼。
You may be thinking, 'There are three stages, so why am I going to edit in stage 3?' The first reason is related in security.
你可能會想，總共有三個階段，為甚麼我們要編輯第三階段的程式碼？背後的原因便是安全性。
The kernel must always handle an exception for the value sent by the users.
內核必須在處理所有由使用者傳送的數值之時，都必須進行例外處理。
For example, the users can pass an invalid integer to the kernel rather then signal number, so it must always be checked.
舉例來說，使用者可能傳送一個不合規範的信號碼(signal number)，這樣的情況一定需要被檢查。
Secend we should check the process, which is to make sure that the
第二，我們應該檢查行程，意思是確保...
target is alive on the current system.
目標行程在系統內是存活(alive)的。
If the process does not exist, there is no need to handle the signal.
如果目標行程並不存在，就不需要處理這個訊號。
Also, if there are multiple threads in one process, you need to check which thread to send to.
再加上，如果在一個行程中有多個執行緒，你需要檢查應該把訊號傳送至哪個執行緒。
Then, you have to check for null pointers at the code level,
之後，你需要檢查在程式碼層級檢查空指標。
and there must be many other things such as security.
以及許多其他事情，例如安全性考量。
Now we understand the reason for doing it in stage 3, but how should we fix it?
現在我們了解為何應該編輯第三階段的程式碼，那我們該如何實行？
In a nutshell, first, we will filter out all signals that is unnecessary in tracing.
簡短而言。第一，我們應該篩選掉所有不必要的訊號。
By printk, we'll output the results to a console.
使用指令"printk"，我們將把結果輸出到主控台(console)。
In the content, the process name and PID in the Sender, the process name and PID in the Receiver, and the signal number are output.
在內容中，傳送者及接收者的行程名稱及PID，加上信號碼都會被輸出。
This is a simple patch I made based on the information we looked at earlier
這是我做得的一個簡單的補丁，基於剛剛我們需要的資訊。
I modified it to filter SIGCHLD and SIGALRM and output Sender and Receiver and signal numbers.
我使它篩選出SIGCHLD及SIGALRM，加上輸出傳送者、接收者及信號碼。
This is the Kernel call stack executed when the 'kill' system-call is called,
這是在"kill"系統呼叫執行時，內核的呼叫堆積(call stack)。
and after processing stages 1 and 2, it is adjusted to output after complete_signal is completed in the send_signal function.
在結束了階段一及階段二的處理之後，在send_signal函式內，在complete_signal完成之後將會輸出。
From now on, I will show you briefly using the system to which the aforementioned patch is applied.
在此之後，我將會簡短的操作一個套用了前述補丁的系統。
This terminal is currently connected to the Raspberry Pi.
這個終端目前連接於樹梅派(Raspberry Pi)。
Currently doing a reboot.
目前正在重新啟動。
We will continue to explain after booting.
我們將在啟動完畢之後繼續解說。
Now the booting is complete, let's analyze the boot message slowly.
現在啟動已經完成，我們來慢慢分析啟動訊息(boot message)。
As we can see here, before the file system is initialized in the boot phase,
我們可以看到，在檔案系統初始化以前。
As the signal can be transmitted as shown above, it is difficult to use the tracing tool described above.
此時信號如前述，可以被傳輸，但是很難用前面提到的工具追蹤。
If you hack the kernel and analyze it, you can easily check it like this.
如果你分析內核，你可以像這樣很簡單的檢查它。
Again, here is a message that the file system is being initialized and a signal is sent before that, and then we will send a
再重複一次，這是檔案系統初始化的資訊，而且在他完成之前將會送出一個訊號。
signal through the kill command in the shell.
我們將會在Shell裡通過"kill"指令送出一個信號。
Using this 'kill' command, I'm going to send a signal to the DHCP client,
我將使用"kill"指令傳送一個信號給DHCP client。
and now I'm going to send a signal using the command.
現在我要使用這條指令來傳送信號。
Then, as you can see in the kernel message, the Sender becomes the shell and the Reciever becomes the DHCP client in the shell.
接下來，如你所見在內核訊息中，傳送者為Shell，接收者則為Shell中的DHCP client。
You can confirm that the SIGUSR1 signal is delivered through the message.
你可以透過訊息確認SIGUSR1的訊號已經傳送。
Next, I will show you how the signal works when rebooting through the reboot command.
接下來，我將向你展示在"reboot"(重新啟動)指令下信號如何運作。
I ran the reboot command.
我運行"reboot"指令。
This will be
我將在...
explained when the reboot process is completed to some extent.
重新啟動完成之後再做說明。
The reboot is now almost complete.
重新啟動幾乎要完成了。
I will explain the contents of the signal generated through the reboot command.
我將解釋"reboot"指令所生成的信號內容。
First, when the reboot command is executed, a signal is sent to all processes in the current system.
首先，當"reboot"指令執行時，將會發送一個信號給所有運行中的行程。
In the case of number 15, it becomes the SIGTERM signal number.
當數值等於15之時，便是SIGTERM的信號碼。
In this way, when the process is completely terminated, a reboot is performed.
以這樣的方法，當所有行程都被終結之後，重新啟動便會被順利地執行。
Therefore, it is possible to analyze what kind of signals are invoked while rebooting through the kernel hacking.
因此，在重新啟動的過程中，是有可能透過內核修改達到分析訊號的目的。
So, let's finish the demo demonstration and go back to the presentation.
現在讓我們結束演示並回到報告。
In this session, rather than deeply analyzing the kernel, I explained from the point of view that there was a certain issue and it was solved by modifying the kernel to solve it.
在這次的報告中，與其對內核有非常深入的了解，我自因問題發生而修改內核的角度解釋。
I'm glad you've gotten even a little closer to the kernel,
我很高興你對於內核有更深的了解。
and I'll end my presentation here.
我也在將在這裡結束我的報告。
Thank you!
謝謝大家。